<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The confession of faith of the Kirk of Scotland subscribed by the Kings Maiestie and his housholde, in the yeare of God 1580. With a designation of such acts of Parlament, as are expedient, for justefying the vnion, after mentioned. And subscribed by the nobles, barrons, gentlemen, burgesses, ministers and commons, in the yeare of God 1638.</title>
            <title>Confession of faith (1581)</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68713</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22026</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121507</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856687</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856687</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22300</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68713)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22300)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 665:18 or 1841:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The confession of faith of the Kirk of Scotland subscribed by the Kings Maiestie and his housholde, in the yeare of God 1580. With a designation of such acts of Parlament, as are expedient, for justefying the vnion, after mentioned. And subscribed by the nobles, barrons, gentlemen, burgesses, ministers and commons, in the yeare of God 1638.</title>
                  <title>Confession of faith (1581)</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>G. Anderson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1638]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The Confession of 1581.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>In this edition B1r line 9 begins: they were publickly ..</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 22026a at reel 665:18, and as 22026.6 at reel 1841:5.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in the Folger Shakespeare Library and Union Theological Seminary Library (New York, N.Y.).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland --  Creeds --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22300:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22300:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Confeſſion of Faith Of the KIRK of SCOTLAND, SVBSCRIBED By the Kings Majeſtie and his Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, in the yeare of God, 1580.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With a Deſignation of ſuch acts of Parlament, as are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, for juſtefying the Vnion, after mentioned.</hi> 
            </p>
            <p>And ſubſcribed by the Nobles, Barrons, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Burgeſſes, Miniſters, and Commons, in the yeare of God, 1638.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>IOSHVA Chap. 24. verſ. 25.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>So Joſhua made a Covenant with the people the ſame day, and gave them an Ordinance and Law in Sichem.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 KINGS 11.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And Jehojada made a Covenant betweene the Lord and the King, and the people, that they ſhould bee the Lords people: likewiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the King and the people.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ISAIAH. 44.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>One ſhall ſay, I am the Lords: another ſhall be called by the name of Jacob: and another ſhall ſubſcribe with his hand unto the Lord, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:22300:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22300:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="royal_charge">
            <pb facs="tcp:22300:3"/>
            <head>The Kings Majeſties Charge, to all Commiſſioners and Miniſters, within this Realme, in the yeare of God <hi>1580.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SEeing that Wee, and our Houſholde, have Subſcribed and given this publick Confeſſion of our Faith, to the good example of our Subjects: We commaund and charge all Commiſſioners and Miniſters, to crave the ſame Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of their Parochinars, and proceed againſt the refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, according to our Lawes and order of the Kirk, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering their names, and lawfull proces to the Miniſters of our Houſe, with all haſte and diligence, under the paine of fourtie pound to be taken from their ſtipend, that Wee, with the advice of our Counſell, may take order with ſuch proud contemners of GOD and our Lawes.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Subſcribed with our hand, at</hi> Halyrudhouſe, <date>1580. <hi>The</hi> 2. <hi>day of March, the</hi> 14. <hi>yeare of our Reigne.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="confession_of_faith">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:22300:3"/>
            <head>The Confeſſion of Faith, <hi>OF The Kirke of</hi> SCOTLAND.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe Confeſſion of Faith, ſubſcribed at firſt by the Kings Majeſtie and his Houſhold, in the yeare of God</hi> 1580. <hi>Thereafter, by Perſons of all rankes, in the yeare</hi> 1581, <hi>By ordinance of the Lords of the Secret Counſell, and Acts of the generall Aſſembly. Subſcribed againe by all ſorts of Perſons in the yeare</hi> 1590, <hi>By a new Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Counſell, at the deſire of the generall Aſſembly: With a generall Band for maintenance of the true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and the Kings Perſon. And now ſubſcribed in the yeare</hi> 1638. <hi>By <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, Noblemen, Barrons, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Burgeſſes, Miniſters, and Commons, vnder ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing: Together, with our reſolution and promiſes for the cauſes after ſpecified, To maintaine the ſayd true Religion, and the Kings Majeſtie, according to the Confeſſion foreſayd, and Acts of Parlament. The Tenor whereof heere followeth.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE All, and every one of Us underwritten, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, that, after long and due Examination of our owne Conſciences, in matters of true &amp; falſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, are now throughly reſolved of the Trueth, by the Word and Spirit of God, &amp; therefore we believe with our hearts, confeſſe with our mouths, ſubſcribe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:22300:4"/>with our hands, and conſtantly affirme before God, and the whole Word: that this onely is the true Chriſtian Faith and Religion, pleaſing God, and bringing Salvation to man, which now is by the mercie of God revealed to the world, by the preaching of the bleſſed Evangell.</p>
            <p>And receaved, believed, and defended, by many and ſundry notable Kirkes and Realmes, but chieflie by the <hi>Kirk of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, the Kings Majeſtie, and three estates of this Realme,</hi> as Gods eternall Trueth, and onely ground of our Salvation: as more particularlie is expreſſed in the Confeſſion of our Faith, ſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and publicklie confirmed by ſundry Acts of Parliaments, and now of a long time hath beene openlie profeſſed by the Kings Majeſtie, and whole body of this Realme, both in Burgh and Land. To the which Confeſſion and forme of Religion, wee willinglie agree in our conſciences in all points, as unto Gods undoubted Trueth and Veritie, grounded onely upon his written Word. And therefore, we abhorre and deteſt all contrarie Religion, and Doctrine: But chieflie, all kinde of Papiſtrie, in generall and particular heads, even as they are now damned and confuted by the <hi>Word of God, and Kirk of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> but in ſpeciall wee deteſt and refuſe the uſurped au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of that Roman Antichriſt upon the Scriptures of God, upon the Kirk, the civill Magiſtrate, and conſciences of men, All his tyrannous lawes made upon indifferent things againſt our Chriſtian libertie, His erroneous Doctrine, againſt the ſufficiencie of the written Word, the perfection of the Law, the office of Chriſt, and his bleſſed Evangell. His corrupted Doctrine concerning originall ſinne, our naturall inabilitie and rebellion to Gods Law, our Iuſtification by faith only, our imperfect Sanctification and obedience to the Law, the nature; number and uſe of the Holy Sacraments. His five baſtard Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, with all his Rites, Ceremonies, and falſe Doctrine, added to the miniſtration of the true Sacraments without the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:22300:4"/>Word of God. His cruell judgement againſt Infants, depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting without the Sacrament: his abſolute neceſſitie of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme: his blaſphemous opinion of Tranſubſtantiation, or reall preſence of Chriſts body in the Elements, and receiving of the ſame by the wicked, or bodies of men. His diſpenſations with ſolemne Oathes, Perjuries, and degrees of Mariage forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the Word: his crueltie againſt the innocent divorced: his divelliſh Maſſe: his blaſphemous Prieſthood: his profane Sacrifice for the ſinnes of the dead and the quicke: his Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zation of men, calling upon Angels or Saints departed, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of Imagerie, Relicts, and Croſſes, dedicating of Kirks, Altars, Dayes, Vowes to creatures; his Purgatorie, Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for the dead, praying, or ſpeaking in a ſtrange language, with his Proceſſions and blaſphemous Letanie, and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Advocates or Mediators: his manifold Orders, Auri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Confeſſion: his deſperate and uncertaine Repentance; his generall and doubtſome Faith; his ſatisfactions of men for their ſinnes: his Iuſtifications by works, <hi>opus operatum,</hi> works of Supererogation, Merits, Pardons, Peregrinations, and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: his holy water, baptiſing of Bells, conjuring of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, croſſing, ſaning, anointing, conjuring, hallowing of <hi>GODS</hi> good creatures, with the ſuperſtitious opinion, joyned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with: his worldlie Monarchie, and wicked Hierarchie: his three ſolemne vowes, with all his ſhavelings of ſundrie ſorts, his erroneous, and bloudie decrees made at <hi>Trent,</hi> with all the ſubſcribers and approvers of that cruell and bloudie Band, conjured againſt the Kirk of <hi>GOD:</hi> and finallie, wee deteſt all his vaine Allegories, Rites, Signes and Traditions, brought in the Kirk, without, or againſt the Word of <hi>GOD,</hi> and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of this true reformed Kirk; to the which wee joyne our ſelves willinglie, in Doctrine, Faith, Religion, Diſcipline, and uſe of the Holy Sacraments, as lively members of the ſame, in Chriſt our Head: promiſing and ſwearing by the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:22300:5"/>
               <hi>Great Name of the Lord our GOD,</hi> that wee ſhall continue in the obedience of the Doctrine and Diſcipline of this Kirk, and ſhall defend the ſame according to our vocation and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, all the dayes of our lives, under the paines contained in the Law, and danger both of Body and Soule, in the day of <hi>GODS</hi> fearefull Iudgement: and ſeeing that many are ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up by Sathan, and that Roman Antichriſt, to promiſe, ſweare, ſubſcribe, and for a time uſe the holy Sacraments in the Kirk, deceitfullie againſt their owne conſciences, mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby, firſt, under the externall cloake of Religion, to corrupt and ſubvert ſecretlie <hi>GODS</hi> true Religion within the Kirk, and afterward, when time may ſerve, to become open enemies and perſecutors of the ſame, under vaine hope of the Popes diſpenſation, deviſed againſt the Word of <hi>GOD,</hi> to his greater confuſion, and their double condemnation in the day of the LORD IESUS.</p>
            <p>Wee, therefore, willing to take away all ſuſpition of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, and of ſuch double dealing with <hi>GOD</hi> and his Kirk, Proteſt, and call <hi>The Searcher of all hearts</hi> for witneſſe, that Our mindes and hearts, doe fully agree with this our <hi>Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Promiſe, Oath,</hi> and <hi>Subſcription,</hi> ſo that We are not mooved for any wordly reſpect, but are perſwaded onely in our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, through the knowledge and love of Gods true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, printed in Our hearts, by the holy Spirit, as wee ſhall anſwere to him in the day, when the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall bee diſcloſed. And becauſe wee perceave, that the quietnes and ſtabilitie of our Religion and Kirk, doth depend upon the ſafetie and good behaviour of the Kings Majeſtie, as upon a comfortable inſtrument of Gods mercie; graunted to this Countrey, for the maintaining of his Kirk, and miniſtration of Iuſtice amongſt us, wee proteſt and promiſe with our hearts under the ſame Oath, Hand-writ, and paines, that wee ſhall defend his Perſon and Authoritie, with our goods, bodies,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:22300:5"/>and lives, in the defence of Chriſt his Evangell, Liberties of our Countrie, miniſtration of Iuſtice, and puniſhment of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, againſt all enemies within this Realme, or without, as wee deſire our <hi>GOD</hi> to bee a ſtrong and mercifull defender to us in the day of our death, and comming of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> To whom with the Father, and the holy Spirit, bee all Honour and Glorie Eternallie.</p>
            <p>LIKE as many Acts of Parlament not onely in generall doe abrogate, annull, and reſcind all Lawes, Statutes, Acts, Conſtitutions, Canons, civill or municipall, with all other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances and practique penulties whatſoever, made in preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of the true Religion and Profeſſours thereof: Or, of the true Kirk diſcipline, juriſdiction, and freedome thereof: Or in favours of Idolatrie and Superſtition: Or of the Papiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Kirk: As, <hi>Act</hi> 3. <hi>Act.</hi> 31. <hi>Parl.</hi> 1. <hi>Act.</hi> 23. <hi>Parl.</hi> 11. <hi>Act.</hi> 114. <hi>Parl.</hi> 12. of <hi>King James the ſixt,</hi> That Papiſtrie &amp; Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may bee utterly ſuppreſſed according to the intention of the Acts of Parlament repeated in the 5. <hi>Act. Parl.</hi> 20. <hi>K. Iames</hi> 6. And to that end they ordaine all Papiſts &amp; Prieſts to bee puniſhed by manifolde Civill and Eccleſiaſticall paines, as adverſaries to Gods true Religion, preached, and by Law eſtabliſhed within this Realme, <hi>Act.</hi> 24. <hi>Parl.</hi> 11. <hi>K. James.</hi> 6. as common enemies to all Chriſtian governement, <hi>Act.</hi> 18. <hi>Parl.</hi> 16. <hi>K. Iames</hi> 6. as rebellers and gainſtanders of our Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne Lords Authoritie, <hi>Act.</hi> 47. <hi>Parl.</hi> 3. <hi>K. Iames</hi> 6. and as Idolaters. <hi>Act.</hi> 104. <hi>Parl.</hi> 7. <hi>K. Iames</hi> 6. but alſo in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar (by and attour the Confeſſion of Faith) doe aboliſh and condemne the Popes Authoritie and Iuriſdiction out of this Land, and ordaines the maintainers thereof to bee puniſhed, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. <hi>Parl.</hi> 1. <hi>Act.</hi> 51. <hi>Parl.</hi> 3. <hi>Act.</hi> 106. <hi>Parl.</hi> 7. <hi>Act.</hi> 114. <hi>Parl.</hi> 12. <hi>K. Iames</hi> 6. doe condemne the Popes erroneous doctrine, or any other erroneous doctrine repugnant to any of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:22300:6"/>of the true and Chriſtian religion publickely preached, and by law eſtabliſhed in this Realme: And ordaines the ſpreaders and makers of Bookes or Libels, or Letters, or writts of that nature to be puniſhed, <hi>Act.</hi> 46. <hi>Parl.</hi> 3. <hi>Act.</hi> 106. <hi>Parl.</hi> 7. <hi>Act.</hi> 24. <hi>Parl.</hi> 11. <hi>K. Iames</hi> 6. doe condemne all Baptiſme conforme to the Popes Kirke and the Idolatrie of the Maſſe, and ordaines all ſayers, willfull hearers, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealers of the Maſſe, the maintainers and reſetters of the Prieſts, Ieſuites, traffiquing Papiſts, to bee puniſhed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any exception or reſtriction, <hi>Act.</hi> 5. <hi>Parl.</hi> 1. <hi>Act.</hi> 120. <hi>Parl.</hi> 12. <hi>Act.</hi> 164. <hi>Parl.</hi> 13 <hi>Act.</hi> 193. <hi>Parl.</hi> 14. <hi>Act.</hi> 1. <hi>Parl.</hi> 19. <hi>Act.</hi> 5. <hi>Parl.</hi> 20. <hi>K. Iames</hi> 6. doe condemne all erroneous bookes and writtes conteining erroneous doctrine againſt the Religion preſentlie profeſſed, or conteining ſuperſtitious Rites and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies Papiſticall, whereby the people are greatly abuſed, and ordaines the homebringers of them to be puniſhed, <hi>Act.</hi> 25. <hi>Parl.</hi> 11. <hi>K. James</hi> 6. doe condemne the monuments and dregs of bygane Idolatrie, as, goeing to the Croſſes, obſerving the Feaſtivall dayes of Saincts, and ſuch other ſuperſtitious and Papiſticall Rites, to the diſhonour of <hi>GOD,</hi> contempt of true Religion, &amp; foſtering of great errour among the people, and ordaines the uſers of them to be puniſhed for the ſecond fault as Idolaters, <hi>Act.</hi> 104. <hi>Parl.</hi> 7. <hi>K. James</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>Like as many acts of Parliament are conceaved for mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of <hi>Gods</hi> true and Chriſtian Religion, and the puritie thereof in Doctrine and Sacraments of the true Church of God, the libertie and freedome thereof, in her nationall, Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodall Aſſemblies, Presbyteries, Seſſions, Pollicie, Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and Juriſdiction thereof, as that puritie of Religion and libertie of the Church was uſed, profeſſed, exerciſed, preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and confeſſed according to the reformation of Religion in this Realme. As for inſtance, <hi>the</hi> 99. <hi>Act. Parl.</hi> 7. <hi>Act.</hi> 23. <hi>Parl.</hi> 11. <hi>Act.</hi> 114. <hi>P.</hi> 12. <hi>Act.</hi> 160. <hi>Parl.</hi> 13. <hi>of K. James</hi> 6. Ratified
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:22300:6"/>by the 4. <hi>Act</hi> of King <hi>Charles.</hi> So that the 6. <hi>Act. Parl.</hi> 1. and 68. <hi>Act. Parl.</hi> 6. of King <hi>James</hi> 6. in the yeare of God 1579. declares the Miniſters of the bleſſed Evangell, whom <hi>GOD</hi> of his mercie had raiſed up, or hereafter ſhould raiſe, agreeing with them that then lived in Doctrine, and Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, and the people that profeſſed Chriſt, as he was then offered in the Evangell, and doth communicate with the holy Sacraments, (as in the reformed Kirkes of this Realme they were publickly adminiſtrate) according to the Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Faith, to bee the true and holy Kirk of Chriſt Jeſus within this Realme, and decernes and declares all and ſundrie, who either gaineſayes the Word of the Evangell, received and approved, as the heads of the Confeſſion of Faith, profeſſed in Parlament, in the yeare of God 1560. ſpecified alſo in the firſt Parlament of King <hi>James</hi> 6. and ratified in this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament, more particularly do ſpecifie, or that refuſes the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the holy Sacraments, as they were then miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to bee no members of the ſaid Kirk within this Realme, and true Religion, preſently profeſſed, ſo long as they keepe themſelves ſo divided from the ſocietie of Chriſts body: And the ſubſequent <hi>Act.</hi> 69. <hi>Parl.</hi> 6. <hi>of K. Iames</hi> 6. declares, That there is none other Face of Kirk, nor other Face of Religion, then was preſently at that time, by the Favour of <hi>GOD</hi> eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed within this Realme, which therefore is ever ſtiled, <hi>Gods true Religion, Chriſts true Religion, the true and Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and a perfect Religion</hi> Which, by manifold acts of Parlament all within this Realme, are bound to profeſſe to ſubſcribe the articles thereof, the Confeſſion of Faith, to recant all doctrine &amp; errours, repugnant to any of the ſaid Articles, <hi>Act.</hi> 4. <hi>and</hi> 9. <hi>Parl.</hi> 1. <hi>Act.</hi> 45.46.47. <hi>Parl.</hi> 3. <hi>Act.</hi> 71. <hi>Parl.</hi> 6. <hi>Act.</hi> 106. <hi>Parl.</hi> 7 <hi>Act.</hi> 24. <hi>Parl.</hi> 11. <hi>Act.</hi> 123. <hi>Parl.</hi> 12. <hi>Act.</hi> 194. <hi>&amp;</hi> 197. <hi>Parl.</hi> 14. <hi>of K. Iames</hi> 6. And all Magiſtrats, Shirefs, &amp;c. on the one parte are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to ſearch, apprehend, and puniſh all contraviners, For
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:22300:7"/>inſtance, <hi>Act.</hi> 5. <hi>Parl.</hi> 1. <hi>Act.</hi> 104. <hi>Parl.</hi> 7. <hi>Act.</hi> 25. <hi>Parl.</hi> 11. <hi>K. Iames</hi> 6. And that notwithſtanding of the Kings Majeſties licences on the contrarie which are diſcharged and declared to bee of no force, in ſo farre as they tend in any wayes, to the prejudice and hinder of the execution of the Acts of Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt Papiſts and adverſaries of true Religion, <hi>Act.</hi> 106. <hi>Parl.</hi> 7. <hi>K. James</hi> 6. On the other part in the 47. <hi>Act. P. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. K. James</hi> 6. It is declared and ordained, ſeeing the cauſe of Gods true Religion, and his highnes Authority are ſo joyned, as the hurt of the one is common to both: &amp; that none ſhall be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as loyall &amp; faithfull ſubjects to our Soveraigne Lord, or his Authority, but be puniſhable as rebellers &amp; gainſtanders of the ſame, who ſhall not give their Confeſſion, and make their profeſſion of the ſaid true Religion, &amp; that they who after de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection ſhall give the Confeſſion of their Faith of new, they ſhall promiſe to continue therein in time comming, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine our Souveraigne Lords Authority, and at the uttermoſt of their power to fortifie, aſſiſt, and maintaine the true Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and Profeſſors of Chriſts Evangell, againſt whatſoever enemies and gaineſtanders of the ſame: and namelie, againſt all ſuch of whatſoever nation, eſtate, or degree they bee of: that have joyned, and bound themſelves, or have aſſiſted, or aſſiſts to ſet forward, and execute the cruell decrees of <hi>Trent,</hi> contrary to the Preachers and true Profeſſors of the Word of God, which is repeated word by word in the Articles of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cification at <hi>Perth</hi> the 23 of Februar. 1572. approved by Parlament the laſt of Aprile, 1573. Ratified in Parlament, 1587. and related, <hi>Act.</hi> 123. <hi>Parl.</hi> 12. <hi>of K. Iames.</hi> 6. with this addition, that they are bound to reſiſt all treaſonable uproares and hoſtilities raiſed againſt the true Religion, the Kings Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and the true Profeſſors.</p>
            <p>Like as all liedges are bound to maintaine the K. Majeſties Royall Perſon, and Authority, the Authoritie of Parlaments,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:22300:7"/>without the which neither any lawes or lawfull judicatories can be eſtabliſhed, <hi>Act.</hi> 130. <hi>Act.</hi> 131. <hi>Parl.</hi> 8. <hi>K. James</hi> 6. &amp; the ſubjects liberties, who ought onely to liue &amp; be governed by the Kings lawes, the common lawes of this Realme allanerlie, <hi>Act.</hi> 48. <hi>Parl.</hi> 3. <hi>K. Iames the firſt. Act.</hi> 79. <hi>Parl.</hi> 6. <hi>K. Iames the</hi> 4. <hi>repeated in the Act.</hi> 131. <hi>Parl.</hi> 8. <hi>K. Iames</hi> 6. Which, if they bee innovated or prejudged, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion anent the union of the two Kingdoms of Scotland &amp; England, which is the ſole <hi>Act. of the</hi> 17. <hi>Parl. of K. Iames</hi> 6. declares ſuch confuſion would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, as this Realme could bee no more a free Monarchie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by the fundamentall lawes, ancient priviledges, offices and liberties of this Kingdome, not onely the Princelie Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of his Majeſties Royall diſcent hath been theſe many ages maintained, but alſo the peoples ſecuritie of their Lands, livings, rights, offices, liberties, and dignities preſerved, and therefore for the preſervation of the ſaid true Religion, Lawes, and Liberties of this Kingdome, it is ſtatute by the 8. <hi>Act Parl.</hi> 1. <hi>repeated in the</hi> 99. <hi>Act. Parl.</hi> 7. <hi>Ratified in the</hi> 23 <hi>Act Parl.</hi> 11. <hi>and</hi> 114. <hi>Act. Parl.</hi> 12. <hi>of K. Iames</hi> 6. <hi>and</hi> 4. <hi>Act. of K. Charles.</hi> That all Kings and Princes at their Coronation &amp; reception of their Princely Authoritie, ſhall make their faithfull promiſe by their ſolemne oath in the preſence of the Eternall God, that, endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the whole time of their liues, they ſhall ſerve the ſame Eternall God to the uttermoſt of their power, according as he hath required in his moſt holy Word, contained in the old and new Teſtament. And according to the ſame Word, ſhall maintaine the true Religion of Chriſt Ieſus, the preaching of his holy Word, the due &amp; right miniſtration of the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts now receaved and preached within this Realme (according to the Confeſsion of Faith immediatelie preceeding) and ſhall aboliſh and gainſtand all falſe Religion contrarie to the ſame, &amp; ſhall rule the people, committed to their charge, according to the will and command of God, revealed in his Foreſaid
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:22300:8"/>Word, and according to the laudable Lawes and Conſtitutions received in this Realme, no wayes repugnant to the ſaid will of the Eternall God, and ſhall procure, to the uttermoſt of their power, to the Kirk of God, and whole Chriſtian people true and perfite peace in all time coming: and that they ſhall bee carefull to roote out of their Empire all Hereticks, and enemies to the true worſhip of God, who ſhall bee convicted by the true Kirk of God, of the foreſaid crimes, which was alſo obſerved by his Majeſtie, at his Coronation in <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> 1633. as may be ſeene in the order of the Coronation.</p>
            <p>In obedience to the Commandement of GOD, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme to the practiſe of the godly in former times, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the laudable example of our Worthy and Religious Progenitors, and of many yet living amongſt us, which was warranted alſo by act of Counſell, commanding a generall band to bee made and ſubſcribed by his Majeſties ſubjects, of all ranks, for two cauſes: One was, For defending the true Religion, as it was then reformed, and is expreſſed in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith, abovewritten, and a former large Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion eſtabliſhed by ſundrie acts of lawfull generall aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, and of Parlament, unto which it hath relation ſett downe in publicke Catechiſmes, and which had beene for many yeares with a bleſſing from Heaven preached, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed in this Kirk and Kingdome, as Gods undoubted trueth, grounded only upon his written Word. The other cauſe was, for maintaining the Kings Majeſtie, His Perſon, and Eſtate: the true worſhip of GOD, and the Kings authoritie beeing ſo ſtraitly joined, as that they had the ſame Friends, and common enemies, and did ſtand and fall together. And final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, being convinced in our mindes, and confeſſing with our mouthes, that the preſent and ſucceeding generations in this Land, are bound to keep the foreſaid nationall Oath and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription inviolable, Wee Noblemen, Barrons, Gentlemen,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:22300:8"/>Burgeſſes, Miniſters, and Commons under ſubſcribing, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering divers times before, and eſpecially at this time, the danger of the true reformed Religion, of the Kings honour, and of the publick peace of the Kingdome: By the manifold innovations and evills generallie conteined, and particularlie mentioned in our late ſupplications, complaints, and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations: Doe heereby profeſſe, and before <hi>God,</hi> his Angels, and the World ſolemnelie declare: That, with our whole hearts wee agree and reſolve all the dayes of our life con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantlie to adhere unto, and to defend the foreſaid true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and (forbearing the practiſe of all novations, alreadie introduced in the matters of the worſhip of GOD, or apro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the corruptions of the publicke Governement of the Kirk or civill places and power of Kirkmen, till they be tryed and allowed in free aſſemblies, and in Parlaments) to labour by all meanes lawfull to recover the puritie and libertie of the Goſpell, as it was eſtabliſhed and profeſſed before the Foreſaid novations: and becauſe after due examination, wee plainelie perceave, and undoubtedlie believe, that the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations and evils conteined in our Supplications, Complaints, and Proteſtations have no warrant of the Word of <hi>God,</hi> are contrarie to the Articles of the Foreſaid Confeſſions to the intention and meaning of the bleſſed reformers of Religion in this Land, to the above writtin Acts of Parlament, and doe ſenſiblie tend to the re-eſtabliſhing of the Popiſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and tyrannie, and to the ſubverſion and ruine of the true Reformed Religion, and of our Liberties, Lawes and Eſtates. Wee alſo declare, that the Foreſaid Confeſſions are to be interpreted, and ought to be underſtood of the Foreſaid novations and evils no leſſe than if every one of them had beene expreſſed in the Foreſaid confeſſions, and that wee are obliged to deteſt and abhore them amongſt other particular heads of Papiſtrie abjured therein. And therefore from the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:22300:9"/>knowledge and conſciences of our duetie to <hi>God,</hi> to our King and Countrey, without any wordly reſpect or inducement, ſo farre as humane infirmitie will ſuffer, wiſhing a further meaſure of the grace of <hi>God</hi> for this effect. We promiſe, and ſweare by the <hi>Great Name of the Lord our GOD,</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the Profeſſion and Obedience of the Foreſaid Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: That we ſhall defend the ſame, and reſiſt all theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie errours and corruptions, according to our vocation, and to the uttermoſt of that power that <hi>GOD</hi> hath put in our hands, all the dayes of our life: and in like manner with the ſame heart, wee declare before <hi>GOD</hi> and Men, That wee have no intention nor deſire to attempt any thing that may turne to the diſhonour of <hi>GOD,</hi> or to the diminution of the Kings greatneſſe and authoritie: But on the contrarie, wee promiſe and ſweare, that wee ſhall, to the uttermoſt of our power, with our meanes and lives, ſtand to the defence of our dread Soveraigne, the Kings Majeſtie, his Perſon, and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, in the defence and preſervation of the foreſaid true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Liberties and Lawes of the Kingdome: As alſo to the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall defence and aſſiſtance, every one of us of another in the ſame cauſe of maintaining the true Religion, and his Majeſties Authoritie, with our beſt counſell, our bodies, meanes, and whole power againſt all ſorts of perſons whatſoever. So that whatſoever ſhall be done to the leaſt of us for that cauſe, ſhall bee taken as done to us all in generall, and to every one of us in particular. And that wee ſhall neither directly nor indirectly ſuffer our ſelves to bee divided or withdrawn by whatſoever ſuggeſtion, allurement, or terrour from this bleſſed and loyall Conjunction, nor ſhall caſt in any let or impediment, that may ſtay or hinder any ſuch reſolution as by common conſent ſhall be found to conduce for ſo good ends. But on the contrarie, ſhall by all lawfull meanes labour to further and promove the ſame, and if any ſuch dangerous and diviſive motion be made
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:22300:9"/>to us by Word or Writ, We, and every one of us, ſhall either ſuppreſſe it, or if need bee ſhall incontinent make the ſame known, that it may be timeouſly obviated: neither do we fear the foule aſperſions of rebellion, combination, or what elſe our adverſaries from their craft and malice would put upon us, ſeeing what we doe is ſo well warranted, and ariſeth from an unfeined deſire to maintaine the true worſhip of God, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie of our King, and peace of the Kingdome, for the common happineſſe of our ſelves, and the poſteritie. And becauſe wee cannot look for a bleſſing from God upon our proceedings, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept with our Profeſſion and Subſcription wee joine ſuch a life and converſation, as beſeemeth Chriſtians, who have renewed their Covenanant with God; Wee, therefore, faithfully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, for our ſelves, our followers, and all other under us, both in publick, in our particular families, and perſonall carriage, to endevour to keepe our ſelves within the bounds of Chriſtian libertie, and to be good examples to others of all Godlineſſe, Soberneſſe, and Righteouſneſſe, and of every duetie we owe to God and Man, and that this our Union and Conjunction may be obſerved without violation, we call the living GOD, the Searcher of our Hearts, to witnes, who knoweth this to be our ſincere Deſire, and unfained Reſolution, as we ſhall anſwere to <hi>JESVS CHRIST,</hi> in the great day, and under the paine of Gods everlaſting wrath, and of infamie, and loſſe of all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and reſpect in this World, Moſt humbly beſeeching the Lord, to ſtrengthen us by his holy Spirit for this end: and to bleſſe our deſires and proceedings with a happie ſucceſſe, that Religion and Righteouſneſſe may flouriſh in the Land, to the glory of <hi>GOD,</hi> the honour of our King, and peace and comfort of us all. In witneſſe whereof wee have ſubſcribed with our hands all the premiſſes, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
